## **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**

sviswa10@asu.edu | 480-399-3390 | linkedin.com/in/sreeaurovindh | github.com/sreeaurovindh |

**Summary** 

Computer Science Ph.D. Student with a strong background in machine learning, big data analytics, software development and statistics. Four years of professional experience in building machine learning models with Scientific Python Stack, R and have worked on extensive independent data science projects.

**Education** 

**Doctor of Philosophy, Computer Science** 

Dec 2018

Arizona State University, Tempe. (GPA 3.63/4.00)

**Master of Science, Computer Science** 

Aug 2014

Arizona State University, Tempe. (GPA 3.52/4.00)

**Bachelor of Engineering, Computer Science** 

May 2010

Anna University, Tamilnadu, India. (GPA 78/100)

Skills

Machine Learning and Statistical Modelling: Experimental design, classification, clustering, regression and model selection, neural nets, support vector machines, and recommender systems

Big data Technology: Map Reduce (Hadoop), Apache Spark, ETL (Pig and Hive) and AWS

Scientific Python Stack: Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn and Jupyter Notebooks

Programming Languages and Databases: Python, R, Java, PHP, SQL, MySQL and MongoDB

**Patents** 

Systems and methods for estimating an impact of changing a source file in a software (US 20140123108)

# Professional Experience

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Dec 2012- Present

Arizona State University, Tempe, United States

- Hypothesized and established different qualitative levels of collaborative human behavior after careful analysis of over 130+ hours of observational study involving student's work on digital tablets
- Developed supervised and unsupervised models that classified quality of user interactions between student pairs using data from a combination of user interaction logs and acoustic and prosodic fingerprint
- Performed feature engineering in R using log features and extracted time-series based features using raw audio data using scientific Python Stack that improved balanced accuracy (BAC) 15% above baseline

#### **System Engineer (Research)**

June 2010- Jul 2012

Software Engineering and Technology Labs, Infosys Labs, Bangalore, India

- Designed and developed bug prediction system that provides various metrics that enabled product managers to gauge the release readiness of the software system
- Clustered millions of commit data and developer profiles using Java and SQL based on their source code version history to provide better resource allocation to various bug fixes

## **Projects**

#### **Experimentation to Evaluate and Enhance Student Experience**

Aug 2017 - present

- Evaluated various invariant and evaluation metrics to measure the effect of the screening test
- Estimated number of samples and statistical power required to conduct a randomized trial
- Evaluated the impact of trial screener on student experience using effect size, significance and sign tests
- Recommended a follow up to reduce early cancellations by measuring total number of hours spent

#### **Search for Sensitive Information in Enron Email Corpus**

July 2017- Aug 2017

- Clustered emails based on dense vector representations of words learned by Word2Vec model and evaluated quality of clusters obtained by various clustering algorithms using Silhouette Coefficient
- Uncovered five high level categories of emails that contains sensitive information such as credit card numbers and bank account information and flagged them for careful analysis

### **Deducing Structure of Web using Common Crawl**

July 2015- Dec 2015

- Sampled and analyzed 154 TB dataset and validated an aggregation algorithm using Java and Python
- Grouped web pages with similar structure across different geo locations with information extracted from raw unstructured html files using Apache Pig

#### Yelp Food Recommender

Jan 2017- April 2017

- Mapped Yelp user reviews to specific food items by combining data from Yelp and Wikipedia by performing text search on Yelp reviews using Apache Solr
- Created a dashboard that compares quality of food items of different restaurants in a specific neighborhood and enabled business owners to understand food quality changes over time

#### **Data Exploration and Recommendation System**

Jan 2015- May 2015

- Created a recommendation system that predicts the expert user who would likely answer the question along with the reasonable time estimate from a corpus of over 2 million posts
- Developed code in R and python in order to perform preprocessing of data by using standard Natural language processing techniques and calculated TF-IDF Score for each term in the document
- Extracted cosine similarity across the entire document corpus to find documents with similar characteristics using apache mahout and amazon web services

#### **Mining Prediction Challenge**

Feb 2015- May 2015

- Built machine learning models using ensemble method with a combination of random forests and support vector machines and validated it using ten-fold cross validation
- Ranked fourth out of fifty teams with 94% balanced accuracy score on classification of the dataset.

#### **Publications**

**Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, and Kurt VanLehn. "High Accuracy Detection of Collaboration from Log Data and Superficial Speech Features." International Society on Learning Sciences 2017.

**Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, and Kurt VanLehn. "Using the tablet gestures and speech of pairs of students to classify their collaboration." IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies (2017)

Girish Makseri Rama, Deepthi Karnam, **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, Srinivas Padmanabamuni, "Bug Prediction Metrics based decision support for Preventive software maintenance", Software Engineering Conference(APSEC) 2012, 2012 19<sup>th</sup> Asia- Pacific

Girish Maskeri Rama, Deepthi Karnam, **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, Srinivas Padmanabamuni,"Version history based source code plagiarism detection in proprietary systems", 2012 28<sup>th</sup> IEEE International conference on Software Maintenance(ICSM), pp.609-612

G Shankar, **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, Gowthamie B, "Swarm based intelligent transition of control from Manned to Unmanned vehicular system using Sun SPOT", International Journal of Computer Applications, February 2010, Volume I, 82-89

# Relevant Coursework

Data Mining, Big Data Computing, Statistical Pattern Recognition, Spoken language processing, Intelligent systems, Design and analysis of algorithms

## Online Coursework

Statistical Learning Online Certificate from Stanford, R Programming, Getting and Cleaning Data, Reproducible Research, Machine Learning

## Masters Thesis

Using the tablet gestures and speech of pairs of students to classify their collaboration.

Advisor: Dr. Kurt VanLehn

## Undergrad Thesis

Dynamic agent discovery and Migration in Small Programmable Object Technology (SPOT) Advisor: Dr. Conor Muldoon (University of Oxford, United Kingdom)